Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is כ״ח. Kaf-Chet. And
we actually start at the top of כ״ח, Kaf-Chet, but just for
some context, we'll go to the very bottom of כ״ז עמוד ב׳.
Kaf-Zayin amud bet.
And we are talking about the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, there's a position of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon in the משנה Mishnah that when a woman has a miscarriage,
if the embryonic sac, the placenta, is filled with liquid but does
not have any visible fetus in it, so the חכמים Chachamim say,
okay, it's a fetus that dissolved. The woman is a יולדת yoledet
and the house is טמא, tamei, there's a dead baby there, even
if it's dissolved. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admits that the woman is
a יולדת, yoledet, clearly there had been a fetus there, but he
says that the house is not טמא, tamei, the fetus no longer
has its status. Why not? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said because
there is a בטל ברוב, batel berov, that within that placenta there's
a majority of other liquids, of embryonic fluid and so on, and
therefore if the fetus is not distinct, it loses its identity. ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish went further and said you don't even need בטל
ברוב, batel berov, as long as its whole appearance has been eradicated,
particularly the face has been wiped away, then it loses its status.
Now what's the reason for this? It's important to remember that תוספות
Tosafot says, I mean, normally we say even a small part of
a corpse causes טומאה, tumah, but תוספות Tosafot points out that you
don't have a corpse here. You don't have, normally we say כזית
kezayit of the flesh or certain amount of bone, but here you
don't have flesh, you don't have bone, you only have stuff that's
sort of liquefied. So therefore, it only causes טומאה tumah by virtue
of it being considered not a quantity of something, but by virtue
of it being considered an entire corpse. And therefore ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, so therefore before they were considered even if a little
piece was missing, but therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it doesn't
have the status of an entire corpse if
it is נתבלבל צורת פניו, nitbalbel tzurat panav, if the face
has been completely sort of you know whatever effaced, eradicated. So therefore
even though physically it's there and it's not בטל, batel, it doesn't
have the status of a corpse once the face has been messed
up. So isn't this like a piece of meat?
A piece of meat has no face.
But that's the point, but there you have meat. You don't have
meat here. If you have a כזית kezayit of flesh, if you
have bone, but you don't have flesh, you don't have bone. All
you have is that there was a whole body here. So to
have that status of an entire corpse, you can say if a
little bit is off, it's not considered the entire corpse. So let's
take a look at that.
So I guess we'll start on the first wide line of כ״ז
עמוד ב׳. Kaf-Zayin amud bet. ריש לקיש אמר שפיר שטרפוהו במימיו נעשה
כמת שנתבלבל צורתו. Reish Lakish amar shepir shetirfuhu be-meimav na'aseh kemet shenitbalbel
tzurato.
If a fetus has been
scrambled with its waters, נעשה כמת שנתבלבל צורתו, na'aseh kemet shenitbalbel tzurato,
that's like a corpse that its shape, maybe it means particularly the
face, we'll see later maybe it means the entire shape, has been
somehow dissolved, destroyed. And therefore it is no longer has a status
of a corpse. You don't need it there to be רוב, rov,
it just needs that its shape and its identity has been destroyed.
אמר ליה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש מת שנתבלבל צורתו מנלן דטהר? Amar
lei Rabbi Yochanan le-Reish Lakish met shenitbalbel tzurato minalan de-tahar?
How do you know that? I want to say you need a
majority because normal ביטול. bitul. How do you know that it's enough
that its shape has been destroyed? אילימא מהא דאמר רבי שבתאי אמר
רבי יצחק מגדלאה ואמרי לה אמר רבי
יצחק מגדלאה אמר רבי שבתאי מת שנשרף. Ilei-ma meihada de-amar Rabbi Shabsai
amar Rabbi Yitzchak Magdala'ah ve-amrei lah amar Rabbi Yitzchak Magdala'ah amar Rabbi
Shabsai met shenisraf.
If a corpse has been burnt. Now when a corpse is burnt,
by the way, it's not what we talked about yesterday about רקב,
rekev, of the rotten, yeah what do you call it,
decomposed body because there it's not burnt,
it's natural decomposition. Burnt is not that, so it's not in that
category. It's not flesh, it's not bone, it's all been burnt. So
it's very analogous in the sense that you had a whole body
here, now you have ashes, it's not flesh, it's not bone, but
it's from a whole body. To what degree is it still considered
like you have the מת? met? And it's a similar concept of
a מת, met, not בשר, basar, not עצמות atzamot and so on.
And it's easy to imagine this initially as charred. We'll talk about
later if it's literally ashes or if it's just burned on the
outside thing, but I think to understand where it's coming from, it's
more easy to understand, let's say you have something that's completely been
charred, okay, but you still see the shape of the body, it's
just been fried to a crisp. Is it, it's not flesh, it's
not bone, it's a מת. met. So what does it mean to
still have that status of a מת? met? So here's what we
said. מת שנשרף, met shenisraf, if it is burnt, ושלדו קיימת, ve-shildo
kayammet, and its form, the body is still present, so we'll see
what that means, טמא. tamei. It causes טומאה. tumah. So there you
see the idea you still need the form.
And it needs it for שרץ sheretz too, right?
What, yeah, but maybe but we're not talking about that. מעשה היה
וטימאו לו פתחים גדולים וטיהרו לו, Ma'aseh hayah ve-timu lo petachim gedolim
ve-teharu lo, top of כ״ח עמוד א׳, Kaf-Chet amud aleph, וטיהרו לו
פתחים קטנים. ve-teharu lo petachim ketanim. So there's a story where they
said the big doors are טמא tamei and the small doors are
טהור. tahor. Now what does that mean? If you have Now what
does that mean? If you have a מת meis in a house
and there is an opening, a window, a טפח על טפח, tefach
al tefach, and let's say it opens into a room, into an
accompaniment, and the window is open, then we say, okay, that the
טומאה tumah goes through that window into the other room. And that
is the concept that טומאה tumah is carried by an opening of
a window of a טפח על טפח. tefach al tefach. Okay, but
there's another הלכה, halacha, even if the windows and doors are closed,
there's a principle
that סוף טומאה לצאת, sof tumah latzeis, the door through which, the
opening through which you will bring the corpse out of the building
is considered like that opening is that door is already open and
the טומאה tumah goes through that door or the doors where it's
likely you will bring the מת meis out of. There's a question
exactly is this biblical, rabbinic, something in between? Anyway, doesn't matter right
now, that's the principle of סוף טומאה לצאת. sof tumah latzeis. Now
that is, here's the הלכה halacha that it is unlikely to bring
a corpse outside of an opening טפח על טפח. tefach al tefach.
Okay, so
if the window was open, it's too small. If the window is
open, then the טומאה tumah would go through, but it's closed and
we have to say the doors where I can imagine you're going
to bring the מת meis out of is as if they're already
open, but the doors where it's unlikely, those are not considered already
open. Okay, so that's the principle, but the big doors save the
small doors. Is that clear? Because the presence of the big doors
means I only focus on those where the טומאה tumah is going
to go out and not the small ones. What? Unless the window
is open, right.
So now, so here we have that you had this body that
was fried to a crisp and it says we made the big
doors that were bigger than four טפחים tefachim טמא tamei because we
assume that the מת meis might go out of those doors and
the windows that were less than four טפחים tefachim but they were
a window but they were closed, those were טהור, tahor, nobody's bringing
it out of a window. Okay, so he says, ah, you see
that because the emphasis is, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying
I'm assuming ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you're looking at this and you're
saying the reason that there's טומאה tumah here is because the מת
meis still has its form. And if this מת meis would not
have its form there would not be טומאה. tumah. That's maybe your
proof. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to say I don't
see how you can infer that from this case. Let's take a
look. דקדקת מינה dekadkat mineh and you presumably ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
want to infer from this teaching, טעמא דצורתו קיימת, taama deshuroto kayemes,
the whole reason you got any problem in this case is because
the form of this corpse is still present. הא לאו הכי, ha
lav hachi, if the form were not present, טהור, tahor, you would
say there would be no טומאה tumah at all. It's burnt to
a crisp, there's no form, no טומאה. tumah. That's what you want
to infer because it emphasizes the form is still there. Says, how
do you know that's the point? He says, דוק מינה להאי גיסא,
duk mineh lehai gisa, I could actually have inferred from that the
exact opposite. What could I have said? צורתו קיימת הוא דטהרו פתחים
קטנים, shuroto kayemes hu deteharu ptachim ktanim, if the form is still
present then when they're going to want to take it out, they're
going to want to keep the form. They're not going to want
to, let's just scoop it all into a container. If you've got
the form, you're going to want to respect that and take it
out in its present form. And therefore you're only going to want
to take it out of a big door. So because its form
is still there, that's why we say it'll be taken out of
the big doors and not the small windows.
הא לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, if the form had not been
there and it was just a pile of ashes, then you could
just as likely have taken it out of a small opening as
a big one. All right, I'm saying window that's high up, let's
say it's not high up, who knows, whatever the case is, and
maybe you could just pass it into the next room, whatever the
case might be. That's a different question of placement, not of size.
But if it was a small, but so if it was not
the form then פתחים קטנים
נמי טמאים, ptachim ktanim nami tmeiyim, even the small ones would be
טמא tamei because they're also candidates that how you'll take it out.
דכל חד וחד חזי לאפוקי אבר אבר, dechol chad vechad chazi leappokei
eivar eivar, because in each one you could take out an individual
limb through a window if it was just all dismembered and piles
of ashes and weren't trying to preserve the entire form. So he
says yes, here is a teaching that talks about a מת meis
having an entire form, but there's no proof from it that without
a burnt מת, meis, if there's no proof from it that without
that form it doesn't have טומאה. tumah. Maybe without that form, the
door you would take it out of would be different and that
would have other implications. So that is the debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. What is the story? And
it is very analogous to this fetus. When you don't have flesh,
you don't have bones, but you have a concept of an entire
מת, meis, what do you need to lose that status? רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said only if it's בטל ברוב batel berov and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said once it basically significantly loses its form, that
is enough. Okay. And again, the emphasis seems not to be צורה
tzurah but here there's not to be on the face as we've
had before, here it seems to be the whole general shape.
Yeah, we don't want to say that, that, you know, regardless of
where this window is, if it's open then someone would go out,
right?
Yeah, but if it's closed, we still have a הלכה halacha of
סוף טומאה לצאת. sof tumah latzeis.
Right, no no I know, I'm just like you're saying
if it's closed
you could have taken it out.
All right, when we're learning טהרות Taharos we can discuss that. Okay,
עולא, Ulla, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, exactly. Okay, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, amar lei Ravina leRav Ashi, so said רבינא Ravina to רב
אשי. Rav Ashi. רבי יוחנן דאמר כמאן *Rabbi Yochanan d'amar keman*? רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* who is saying that even if it's lost its
form, it still is a מת mes *meis*, who is he going
like? So דאמר כמאן *d'amar keman*? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer*.
Now, remember by the way, both רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* are only arguing according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*.
The חכמים *Chachamim* argue on רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and say even
with all of this it's still טמא tamei. *tamei*, but anyway, who
is רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* going like? Like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer.
*Rabbi Eliezer*. Now, we taught in the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. אפר שרופין
*Eifer serufin*, the ashes of corpses that have been burnt. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer* שיעורן ברובע *shiuran berova*. So the
amount that it requires to cause טומאה tumah *tumah* is a quarter
of a קב *kav*, whatever that is. So anyway, the point though
is that you have just ashes here and they cause טומאה tumah
*tumah* even though there is no shape. So that seems to be
a clear proof to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, right? Clear proof to
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that you have no bones, no flesh, just
ashes, and it still causes טומאה tumah *tumah* as long as you
have a certain minimum amount. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says היכי
דמי מת meis. *Heichi dami meis*... Okay, so therefore that seems to
be a clear support of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* or at least
maybe of the חכמים *Chachamim* that argue on רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*.
So now what would we have again? There's a debate in the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. This fetus is dissolved in the placenta. חכמים *Chachamim*
say it still has a status of fetus, causes טומאה tumah *tumah*.
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says it does not. Why not? Two opinions:
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says ביטול ברוב *bitul berov*, that even if it lost its
shape, it still causes טומאה tumah *tumah* until you have a majority
of other liquids overwhelm it. And ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says when
you're not dealing with flesh and with meat but just with a
case like if it's something burnt or something like this dissolves, then
the only טומאה tumah *tumah* is by the entire מת meis, *meis*
and as long as it doesn't keep its form, it is not
considered an entire מת *meis*. And here, according to this opinion of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer* that ashes cause טומאה tumah *tumah*,
is a support to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, you do not need
it to keep its form and you can still have טומאה tumah,
*tumah*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר אביי Amar Abaye
*Amar Abaye*, said אביי *Abaye*, I'm sorry, היכי דמי מת שנשרף וצורתו
קיימת
*Heichi dami meis shenisraf vetzurato kayames*? Going back to that example that
it was burnt but it still retains its form. How do you
get something to retain its form after it's been burnt? So let's
take a look. אמר אביי Amar Abaye, כגון ששרפו על גבי קטבלא
*Amar Abaye kagon shesarfo al gabei katafla*. You burnt it on top
of a קטבלא *katafla* which is basically some type of boiled leather
and apparently the fire wasn't able to affect it or burn through
it. So it burnt but it retained
its place, so you could lift it up on the leather and
it would keep the way exactly it had been when it would
be burnt. Because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* imagines if it burnt on
the floor,
how are you going to keep its form when you're trying to
transport it out of the house? So if it burnt on a
piece of fireproof leather and therefore you are able to just pick
up the leather. Okay, so it says like this, רבא אמר כגון
ששרפו על גבי אפידרא *Rava amar kagon shesarfo al gabei apidra*. So
you burnt it on top of אפידרא *apidra* or רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says אפידרא *apidra* which is basically some type of a marble stone.
Okay, and so same type of an idea and you could lift
it up. I guess it's a marble
platform. Now רש"י *Rashi* adds by the way, רש"י *Rashi* says כגון
שעשויה בדיקולין ומחיצות שאינו יכול להתפזר *kagon she'asuya bedikulin umechitzos she'eino yachol
lehispazer*, that it actually have walls around them that keeps it in
its place. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* even went further that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
says, if you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* "שנשרף על גבי קטבלא"
*shenisraf al gabei katafla*, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says או שהיה בתוך דפוס
של אדם adam, וצורתו *o shehayah besoch dfus shel adam vetzurato*,
that actually the person was in some type of a leather or
marble insert where actually
it was indented around the shape. So even after the body burnt,
the ashes were kept in their position because the body had been
in an indented form inside something. Fit to a T? Yeah exactly.
Okay, so thinking
back into ancient times that yeah, there's no knowledge, maybe how else
would it ever happen to be? I know, but remember the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* having the example before, you buried somebody naked inside of
a marble coffin? So I'm again, I'm not sure exactly how much
it's imagining that this really happened. I don't know, I can't speculate.
Yeah, that's what David just said. Exactly. Right, how else would it,
I can't understand the body, you can say it was
burnt.
Right, that's what I understand, that's what David was asking. Could be.
I don't know enough to comment on whether things like this were
done intentionally. רבינא אמר *Ravina amar*, so רבינא *Ravina* says, which I
think is the easiest way of reading this, כגון דאיחרכי איחרוכי *kagon
de'ichruchi ichruchi*, like
it had been charred. It didn't completely ashes, it had completely charred,
there's no but it's not ashes. Okay, anyway in all those cases
it's not טמא tamei? *tamei* because of flesh or bones, it's only
טמא tamei. *tamei* because of the entire מת *meis*. And there's the
question of maybe only when it retains its shape and its form.
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabbanan*, wrapping this up. המפלת יד חתוכה ורגל חתוכה
אמו טמאה לידה temei'ah leidah. *Hamapeles yad chatucha veregel chatucha imo tmeiah
leidah* ואין חוששין שמא מגופא טומא בה *ve'ein chosheshin shema migufo tuma
bah*.
So if a woman miscarries and just what comes out is just
a limb, a leg, an arm, so you assume of course that
there's obviously טומאה tumah *tumah* from a larger fetus and she's טמאה
tmeia. לידה *tmeiah leidah* even though there's nothing else that you've seen,
somehow it dissolved and came out or whatever, and she's טמאה לידה
*tmeiah leidah*, excuse me. And you're not concerned that the fetus in
her was somehow not naturally forming and would not cause טומאת לידה.
tumas leida, So you assume even though you can't see it, that
there had been a naturally forming fetus. You just somehow it dissolved
and she's טמאה לידה. Fine. באו Ba'u now רב חסדא ורבה בר
רב הונא Rav Chisda ve-Rabbah bar Rav Huna דאמרי תרווייהו. de-amri tarveihu.
Rav Chisda and Rabbah bar Rav Huna
both say אין נותנים לה ימי טוהר. ein notnim lah yemei tohar.
You can't really consider it a definite יולדת. yoledet. She's a ספק
יולדת. safek yoledet. She has טומאה tumah. of a week or two
weeks because it's obviously two weeks after concern it might be a
נקבה, nekeivah, but no טהרה toharah because maybe it wasn't really a
childbirth. Why not? Let's take a look. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אימא
הרחיקה לידתה. Eima hirchikah leidatah. Maybe it was a long time ago,
meaning yeah of course there definitely was a fetus here. But when
did it come out?
Maybe the majority of the body which makes her a יולדת, yoledet,
maybe that came out three weeks ago and one limb stayed and
we didn't see it and one limb stayed in her body and
this one limb came out now. So we're saying she's a definite
יולדת yoledet but we don't know when. And maybe the time of
the טהרה toharah is up by now. So therefore you can't give
her any time of טהרה. toharah.
Does this apply to all the תרומות terumot she touched? Like how
far back do you go?
Isn't that something we've been concerned about the whole time?
Well you mean
why don't we assume that also retroactively there's a ספק טומאה? safek
tumah? Yeah. They're not that concerned. The whole idea of a retroactive
טומאה Tumah which we dealt with from the beginning of the מסכת
masechet was very weak. The גמרא Gemara says דרבנן derabbanan and we're
very lenient about it and there's no evidence per se, but at
least not enough that we're confident enough to give her a טהרה
toharah to say the blood that we actually are going to see
in the next thirty-three days is טהור. tahor.
So release anything she touched even today would be טהור? tahor?
No. Oh, you mean before this arm came out? That's an interesting
question. Like if the arm came out and nothing else did, should
we at least say it came out earlier today? Maybe. That's a
good question. I don't know the answer. That's a good question. Okay,
so it says like this.
Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
that's the reason. Yes, she gave birth but we don't know exactly
when and we can't give her טהור tahor days.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מתיב Metiv רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Rav Yosef asks this. המפלת ואין
ידוע מה היא הפילה. Ha-maplet ve-ein yadu'a mah hi hepilah. So this
is you know this is probably one of the first משניות mishnayot
that should have been in this פרק. perek. The פרק perek always
starts on the more bizarre cases. It looks like an animal, it
looks like this, it looks like that. But the and it all
assumes sort of this later משנה Mishna. or a lot of this
assumes this later משנה Mishna which is a woman who miscarried and
doesn't know whether what the fetus was, a boy or a girl.
Maybe she didn't see the fetus come out, she knows she miscarried
but somehow anyway whatever. So what do you say? תשב לזכר ולנקבה.
Teshev le-zachar u-li-nekeivah.
It's either a boy or a girl, you have to be strict
both ways. So two weeks of טומאה Tumah like a girl but
her טהרה toharah days end at day forty like a boy. That's
the standard rule if you don't know what the story of the
fetus was. Now we are assuming that this case of ואין ידוע
מה היא הפילה ve-ein yadu'a mah hi hepilah does not mean that
she just has a full miscarriage right now we see it but
we can't identify it. It also can include a case where she
doesn't even know exactly when she miscarried. If you've got I guess
imagine that case.
Right, I know. But the reason she doesn't know what is she
didn't see it come out or somehow. I mean it's hard to
exact fast exactly imagine that but anyway. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואי סלקא דעתך Ve-i salka
daitach
if what you כהאי גוונא ke-hai gavna אימא הרחיקה לידתה eima hirchikah
leidatah
if you think that whenever the whole thing doesn't come out in
front of us or
we're concerned that it happened sometime in the distant past, ליחמרו נמי
לנידה lichmeru nami le-niddah
then why doesn't it say that one of the things we're still
strict about is נידה? niddah? What does that mean? So it means
that one minute right it means that were she to bleed when
you say she treats it like a male or a female it
means we're still going to give her טהור tahor days. Right let's
just say her טהור tahor days are going to end at day
forty. But you're telling me that you don't want to give her
any טהור tahor days. So then it should say we're also going
to be strict and treat any blood as נידה niddah blood. Like
you get it if she treats it as a boy or a
girl it means okay one week or two weeks of טומאה tumah
but still טהרה toharah is going to go up through day forty.
And any bleeding from day fifteen to day forty is going to
be okay. But if you're telling me we can't even give her
any טהור tahor days you should say we give her all the
stringencies of boy girl and נידה niddah which means טומאה tumah for
fourteen days and any bleeding afterwards actually you don't even have to
say boy you just have to say girl and נידה. niddah. Fourteen
days of טומאה tumah, regardless and any bleeding afterwards makes her a
נידה. niddah. Now of course you could say that there's an obvious
difference that when it's one limb coming out and you haven't seen
anything else so who knows when the rest came out. But maybe
that's not the scenario here. Maybe the scenario here is she sees
everything coming out she just can't identify it. But the גמרא Gemara
assumes that it's including even cases where something might have happened earlier
you can't be sure and why doesn't it say as well there
that you don't give her טהור tahor days? So let's take a
look. אמר אביי
אי תנא לנידה ei tana le-niddah no really you're right we don't
give her טהור tahor days but it didn't want to say it
why? אי תנא לנידה Ei tana le-niddah if we would say we
give her the stringencies of a נידה niddah הוה אמינא מביאה קרבן
ואינו נאכל hava amina meviah korban ve-eino ne'echal it might have made
it sound like there's a doubt whether... she actually has the status
of a יולדת, yoledet, right? If it says you treat her like
a נידה, niddah, a נידה niddah usually is in contrast to a
יולדת, yoledet, meaning either she's a woman who has given birth or
it's נידה niddah blood. So even if you had used that phrase,
it would have suggested that in this case of miscarriage, we're not
sure if she has that status or not. And what's the big
deal? You're still making her טמא. tamei No, the big deal is
is that then she wouldn't be able to eat her קרבן. korban.
We're saying now she's a definite יולדת, yoledet, we don't know boy
or girl. If you had said boy, girl, or נידה, niddah, it
would have suggested we don't know she's a יולדת yoledet and she
wouldn't have been able to eat her קרבן. korban. קמשמע לן דנאכל.
kamashmalan denachal.
So therefore it says boy or girl to tell you you eat
the קרבן. korban. But basically the גמרא Gemara is saying you're right.
Anytime when you are not certain that the whole miscarriage is coming
out now, you lose your טהור tahor days. So if only an
arm came out or something came out but you're not sure it
was the whole thing, then you lose your טהור tahor days because
you don't know when it actually began. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara. says like
this, okay.
I'm sorry, but if she actually did have bleeding during that time
period, she would still have הלכות הנידה, halachos hanniddah, right?
Before the birth?
No, I mean after this whatever this arm came out, 14 days
of טומאה tumah, in day 15 she bleeds.
Yeah, you don't give her טהור tahor days and then she has
טומאת נידה, tumas niddah, that's exactly the point. Right, but we didn't
want to use that term נידה, niddah, it would have been misleading.
Right. So it says. Right. Okay. אמר
הונא.
Amar
Huna. So says רב הונא, Rav Huna, הוציא עובר ידו והחזירה אמו
טמאה לידה. hotzi ubar yado vehachzira imo tmeia leida. Does that sound
like anything anybody knows? Right, exactly. So if the fetus sticks out
the hand and pulls it back in, that's enough to make the
woman טומאת לידה, which is very strange because we've been saying implicitly
and we're going to say in a minute that the child is
only considered born when the head comes out.
So let's see what this means.
Feet would be the same thing if it put out a foot.
Yeah. So let's see what this thing means. שנאמר shene'emar the פסוק
pasuk says, ויהי בלדתה ויתן יד. vayehi belidta vayiten yad. It was
when she was giving birth and this, you know, he stuck forth
a hand, so that was
זרח, Zarach, right, and then פרץ Peretz bursts forth first. So you
see it says she's giving birth and it says sticks forth a
hand, so that was already considered childbirth. Again, very strange that it's
normally we normally say you need to be at least the head.
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. מתיבי
רב יהודה, Matisvei Rav Yehuda, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda asks on
this, הוציא עובר ידו אין אמו חוששת לכל דבר. hotzi ubar yado
ein imo chosheshas lechol davar. We have a ברייתא braisa that says
that if the fetus sticks out the hand, the mother doesn't have
to be concerned about anything, no טומאה, tumah nothing, it doesn't mean
it's not meaningful for her status. So אמר רב נחמן לדידי מפרשא
לי מיניה דרב הונא, amar Rav Nachman ledidi mefarsha li minei deRav
Huna, that statement of רב הונא Rav Huna was explained to me
where he said sticking out the hand counts, לחוש חוששת. lachush chosheshas.
That
at that stage you're concerned that she might already have been given
birth. ימי טוהר לא יהבינן לה עד דנפיק רוביה. yemei tohar lo
yahavinan lah ad denafik rubei.
But she does not have, she's not considered to definitely be having
given birth until the majority comes out. Again, even the phrase majority
is funny, normally we would say the head. But his basic point
is, you're right, it doesn't have the status of definite birth until
the head or the majority. But doubtful birth begins even when the
arm comes out. So the טומאה tumah days begin, but you cannot
yet give her the טהור tahor days until the later period. חוששת
chosheshas that she actually has to treat herself as טמאה. Okay, so
it's a possible birth but not yet a definite birth. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואינה חוששת לכל דבר קאמר. ve'eina chosheshas lechol davar
ka'amar.
But it says that if it sticks out an arm you don't
have to be concerned about anything, which means no status begins with
just the arm. How can you say that there's some status when
the arm sticks out? So אמר אביי, אינה חוששת לכל דבר מדאורייתא.
einah chosheshas lechol davar midioraisa.
All right, you're right, fine. Okay, biblically there's nothing, no status until
the head comes out or the body comes out, the majority, and
that's actually the next משנה. Mishnah. You're right, nothing really begins until
the head or the majority of the body. אבל מדרבנן aval miderabbanan
חוששת. chosheshas.
Rabbinically we'll say when the arm comes out we're concerned. והא קרא
קאמר, veha kra ka'amar, but it's quoting a פסוק? pasuk? All right,
מדרבנן וקראי אסמכתא בעלמא. miderabbanan u'kraya asmakhta be'alma. It's only rabbinic, the
פסוק pasuk
was just a nice thing to link it to. Now the question
is what does חוששת chosheshas mean? Does חוששת chosheshas mean, all right,
the rabbis are just, you know, like they do in general, they
just play it safe so people won't be able to tell the
difference? Or maybe is it saying that, you know, if an arm
comes out do you have to be concerned that maybe the head
came out and went back in and you just didn't catch it
and didn't see it? That חוששת chosheshas sometimes can mean, right, you
know, you're concerned about things that you don't know about that you
didn't see. So that's an interesting question about, like, you know, about
this idea that now we're saying, although exactly as the next משנה
Mishnah. is going to tell us,
that it's only when the baby crowns or when the majority comes
out is it definitely considered born, to what degree is there some,
you know, rabbinic concern at an earlier stage and when this arm
comes out at least to begin a period of טומאה. tumah, For
example, nobody said anything like this about when it comes to things
other than טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah like,
what do you call it, like let's say נו, nu, like let's
say, well
I'm trying to see where the רמב"ם Rambam brings this down, I
actually didn't look it up, but I certainly know that like when
it comes to ברית מילה bris milah and those types of issues
nobody will say oh the arm came out earlier. You can't you
have to be concerned it's already born on that day and you
can't do the ברית
מילה Bris Milah whatever there it's clearly going to go by the
next משנה. Mishnah. This is only sort of being brought in into
this general area of טומאה Tumah, and טהרה. Taharah.
You're saying he sticks out his arm and it's just considered טמא?
tamei, Let's say he sticks
out his arm on Friday afternoon and the head comes out on
שבת. Shabbos. Nobody's going to say, oh, might be a שבת Shabbos
ברית מילה Bris Milah later though. But there'd be some דרבנן d'rabonon
of טומאה tumah later, right. Okay, yes. Previously when you said that
you treat her strictly as a girl and a boy in terms
of the time. Right.
But then
you
said something about you don't give her any טהרה taharah days. Is
that a debate? Yeah, well that the simple sense was you do
give her the טהרה taharah days, but then according to that opinion
that
the גמרא Gemara was trying to defend, it would be if there
was any concern that the birth had happened early that the that
the fetus had part you know the majority of the fetus had
come out earlier then you wouldn't be able to give her any
טהרה taharah days. So it was a qualification that even though we
normally say you give her the טהרה taharah days up to day
40, according to that opinion we had been dealing with if there
was a doubt whether if there was a doubt whether the child
had maybe the some the majority of the fetus had come out
earlier then you would not be able to give her טהרה taharah
days. So the 80 days would then start from whenever the hand
came out and you know... No, logically that would make sense but
it says ימי טוהר לא יהבינן לה אוד, yemei tohar lo yahavinan
lah od, so it doesn't... it seems like... I know it's ironic
because if you're being מחמיר machmir you should be מחמיר machmir about
the start date. Yeah, I don't know, have to see how the
רמב"ם Rambam looks at that. Let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishna המפלת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Hamapeles tumtum v'androgynus. All right, now we
get to this. So if a woman gives birth to a child
that is a no longer with a fetus, now we're children, but
children but but you know but that have are still unusual cases.
So it is a טומטום tumtum or אנדרוגינוס. androgynus.
אנדרוגינוס Androgynus is obviously the word andro and you know androgynous, male
female. It's a person or a baby here that has both male
and female genitalia. טומטום Tumtum means basically quoted from of course Lewis
Carroll, the Hunting of the Snark, the tumtum tree. No? Nobody?
Anyway. Fine. Anyway, טומטום tumtum is somebody whose genitalia is covered up
and you don't know if it's a male or a female. So
she gives birth to this baby, so you don't know if it's
a boy or a girl. תשב לזכר ולנקבה. Teshev l'zachar ul'nekeiva. So
she has the stringencies of male and female. She has two weeks
טומאה tumah of a female, but only up to day 40 of
טהרה taharah like a male. Now, טומטום וזכר אנדרוגינוס וזכר. Tumtum v'zachar
androgynus v'zachar. Let's say she gave birth to a טומטום tumtum and
a male twin, or an אנדרוגינוס androgynus and a male. תשב לזכר
ולנקבה. Teshev l'zachar ul'nekeiva. This this טומטום tumtum אנדרוגינוס androgynus might be
a female so you have both stringencies. You had a definite male,
possible female, you have both stringencies. טומטום ונקבה אנדרוגינוס ונקבה. Tumtum unekeiva
androgynus unekeiva. So let's say it was a טומטום tumtum and a
female, an אנדרוגינוס androgynus and a female. תשב לנקבה בלבד. Teshev l'nekeiva
bilvad. Then she only has to worry about a female. Why? Because
14 days of טומאה tumah. she definitely has because of her of
the female. And 66 days of טהרה taharah she definitely has because
of the female. So even though it was a definite female and
a male, the male doesn't counteract the 66 days of טהרה taharah
that she gets for the female. She's always in if it's a
definite female she always gets those 66 days of טהרה taharah whatever
else happens. So it's a חומרא chumra of אנדרוגינוס. androgynus. Right. So
if it was two females or a female and a male, it
would also be the same הלכה. halacha. 14 days of טומאה, tumah,
66 days of טהרה. taharah. So a female and אנדרוגינוס? androgynus? Like
a male and a female, you still get longer? That is correct.
That is correct. Because the because the male doesn't say you're not
it doesn't say you don't get טהרה taharah days after this, it
just says the טהרה taharah you get are limited. But at the
same... wouldn't you say with a male and a female, why don't
you just get fewer טהרה taharah days? No. The male doesn't take
away טהרה taharah days. The male gives you a 33-day get-out-of-jail-free card.
The female gives you a 66-day get-out-of-jail-free card. Having the 33 day
doesn't take away your 66 day. Well, you're wrong. Okay, so now
we go on. All right, now we go on. So it says,
so that's the משנה. Mishnah So therefore in that case you don't
have to worry about the טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgynus because the
female gives you everything, maximum טומאה, tumah maximum טהרה. taharah. יצא מחוטך,
Yatza mechutach, now in a totally different teaching about when is the
fetus considered born. Okay, which we've been sort of implying and discussing
until now. If it comes out dismembered או מסורס o mesuras or
backwards, meaning breech baby, feet first, משיצא רובו, misheyatza rubo, then you
don't go by the head because a breech is not coming out
head first and number two if it's dismembered there's not the same
significance to the head. It's just sort of pieces of the fetus.
So then you go by when the majority comes out. הרי הוא
כילוד, Harei hu k'yalud, then it's considered as born. יצא כדרכו, Yatza
k'darko, if it comes out naturally which is as one unit and
the head first, then עד שיצא רוב ראשו, ad sheyatza rov rosho,
the majority of the head. איזהו רוב ראשו? Eizehu rov rosho? What
is the majority of the head? משיצא פדחתו, Misheyatza pachto, the forehead.
Now that sounds pretty funny because normally you think that a forehead
is like is like a third or whatever but when you take
drawing classes they show you make an oval, you know make a
horizontal line and a vertical line and that horizontal line smack in
the middle that's where the eyes start. So actually the forehead is
like half of of the face. We normally don't think that way
but actually it's true. But also with babies it's more elongated as
it is. That could be too. Okay, so that, the second part
has to do with when you define the moment of birth, the
third part, which is very central, the first part is the stranger
case of the טומטום Tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. Androgynus. Let's see the גמרא.
Gemara השתא טומטום לחודיה ואנדרוגינוס לחודיה אמרת יש בו זכר ונקבה, Hashta
tumtum lechudei ve'androgynus lechudei amrat yesh bo zachar venekevah, if you just
have a טומטום tumtum or an אנדרוגינוס androgynus you have to be
strict about male and female, you have to have both stringencies. טומטום
זכר ואנדרוגינוס וזכר מיבעי? tumtum zachar ve'androgynus vezachar mibe'ei? Who needs to
tell me the case of a טומטום tumtum and a male and
an אנדרוגינוס androgynus and a male? Of course you'll have both stringencies
as a זכר zachar certainly, you know, why should I think that
that would be any different? So I mean the interesting case is
of course the טומטום tumtum and the female, the אנדרוגינוס androgynus and
the female, because there it's saying that once you have one female
the other fetus doesn't matter. But if you have the טומטום tumtum
and the male and then you're telling me treat it as male
female, how is that a bigger telling me anything that I didn't
know if you had just one טומטום tumtum and male and female?
Now of course you could say that the משנה was just leading
up to the next case. You're right, the טומטום tumtum and the
male is not telling you anything unusual, the טומטום tumtum and the
female was the bigger חידוש. chiddush. But the גמרא Gemara asks why
did I have to tell me the case of the טומטום tumtum
and the male if it's the exact same הלכה halacha as the
טומטום tumtum by himself? So the גמרא Gemara says איצטריך. itsterich. I
need it, and that's going to say something it said earlier, מהו
דתימא mahu d'teima because basically it's saying remember earlier it said I
might have thought that the likelihood of boy girl twins is very
unlikely. And because I might have thought that the likelihood of boy
girl twins is unlikely, I could assume that if you have a
טומטום tumtum and a male what we're really dealing with here is
two males. Okay meaning an אנדרוגינוס androgynus we see everything, we see
both genitalia, we don't know how to categorize it, but a טומטום
tumtum is a male or female we just don't know. So if
I assume that it's very unlikely to have boy girl twins and
you have a טומטום tumtum and a male, maybe I have a
right to assume that it's two males. Okay and therefore it has
to tell me no you have to assume it could even be
a female, that boy girl twins is not so unlikely and therefore
even a טומטום tumtum and a male you have to treat as
a male and a female. What? רוב ככל הרוב? rov kechal harov?
Well or we it's not proved that it is a רוב rov
either way. Okay so it says like this so the גמרא Gemara
says איצטריך, itsterich, I need it. מהו דתימא mahu d'teima I might
have thought הואיל ואמר רבי יצחק אישה מזרעת תחילה יולדת זכר איש
מזריע תחילה יולדת נקבה ho'il ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak isha mazra'at techila yoledet
zachar ish mazria techila yoledet nekeva if a woman gives forth seed
first meaning she reaches she orgasms first then the conceived child will
be a male, if the man gives forth seed first it'll be
a female, so I might have thought it's either one or the
other and even in the case of twins it'll either be two
boys or two girls, one of them either one happened or the
other happened, you can't get a boy and a girl. So therefore
אימא מידהאי זכר אינהו זכר eima midehai zachar einhu zachar if one
is a male the other's a male, at least by the case
of טומטום tumtum presumably not by אנדרוגינוס androgynus because we know that's
different. But a boy and a טומטום tumtum I would assume two
boys, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so this teaches you that
it's not that we can't assume that, we have to say it
could be a boy and a girl. Why? אימא שניהם הזריעו בבת
אחת eima sheneihem hizriu bevat achat maybe both of them gave forth
seed, the husband and the wife at the same time and therefore
that would allow for the possibility of it being both a boy
and a girl. Just out of curiosity in fraternal twins is there
any greater percentage of boy boy and boy girl like same sex
and different sex? I don't think there is, I think it's just
that it would be probably 50% boy girl and 25% boy boy
and 25% girl girl and of course identical twins which are much
rarer have to be the same sex because they're genetically identical. But
of course if that's true, which I would assume also, then in
any set of twins where one of them is a boy it
is more likely that the other one is a girl. Yes if
you I mean at least in fraternal twins because the probability of
identical twins is not zero. No no no no even without excluding
identical twins it's in a normal population of fraternal twins is 25%
girl girl 25% boy boy 50% boy girl. Right so if you
have the first one is a boy then it's only in one
third of the cases is the other one a boy and in
two thirds of the cases the other one is a girl. Yeah
that's a conditional probability. Yeah okay so there's statistics on that, I'll
try to come up. All right even if you add the identical
twins I think the statistics are the opposite of what the גמרא
Gemara said, that if one is a boy even with identical twins
it's more likely the other is a girl because they're actually slightly
it's not exactly 50% males and females. All right you'll tell us.
Anyway anyway so that's what it's telling me according to the גמרא
Gemara that's what it's telling me that even if you know the
sex of one you have to assume the other sex might be
the other and therefore by a boy you're concerned about boy girl
and by a girl it doesn't really matter what the other sex
is and it has the 14 days and the 66 days. Okay
now the גמרא Gemara says like this all right זו זכר וזו
נקבה zu zachar vezu nekeva so therefore you're going to have a
male and a female that was from the end of the previous
statement if they both were מזריע mazria at the same time. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רב טומטום ואנדרוגינוס שראו לובן או אודם אין חייבין
על ביאת מקדש ואין שורפין עליהם את התרומה. Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rav Tumtum ve'Androgynus sherau loven o odem ein chayavin al biat mikdash
ve'ein sorfin aleihem et haterumah. So you have a טומטום tumtum and
אנדרוגינוס. androgynus. And they basically see some semen or blood. Now by
the טומטום tumtum it would be that something is coming out of
the genital area; you have to assume that there's a skin covering
over the genitals, but there's some hole for things to come out
of, I mean, otherwise how's the person urinate? Okay, but that would
be the case by the טומטום, tumtum, and out of that hole
comes blood or semen. Or in the case of the אנדרוגינוס, androgynos,
where he has both genitalia, you're having semen coming out of the
penis, or you're having blood coming out of the vagina. And what
is their הלכה? halacha? Is it—is this person a בעל קרי, ba'al
keri, a נדה, niddah, right? What's the status? So it says ספק.
safek. Now in the טומטום, tumtum, what's the ספק? safek? The ספק
safek is is that well, maybe the genitalia is the opposite. Maybe
the—this person has female genitalia, and the semen is coming out from
some bizarre way, okay, who knows? Or it looks like semen, it's
not really semen. Or the easier one to imagine is maybe he
has male genitalia and blood is coming out because he's got a
cut, but it doesn't mean that he's a נדה. niddah. So that's
easy. But the—that you have to say it's ספק, safek, although you
wonder how it happens. But in the case by the אנדרוגינוס, androgynos,
it's a little more surprising. You would think if you see semen
out of the male genitalia, coming out of the male genitalia, or
blood coming out of the female, you would think that that clearly
makes him a בעל קרי ba'al keri or a נדה. niddah. But
no, because if the personal status—if we can't label—in the טומטום, tumtum,
we don't know what his status is. He is boy or girl;
we just don't know how to label him. In the אנדרוגינוס, androgynos,
because it has both genitalia, we don't know whether we can give
him either label. Maybe we should give him the boy label. Maybe
we should give him the girl label. Maybe we should give him
some third gender label. By the way, people that like, what's that,
you know, transgender—there's this whole movement about sort of challenging normal binary
gender divisions, so they like very much this idea of the אנדרוגינוס,
androgynos, because the גמרא Gemara doesn't say you have to force it
into one or two; it might actually be a third gender. Anyway,
so, so, so—I actually saw from an Orthodox rabbi, that some rabbi
once wrote on the internet how we have to be very sensitive
to these issues, so that when we're like announcing things, we shouldn't
say, 'This event is open to men and women,' we should say,
'This event is open to people of all genders.' So anyway, so
you have this אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. Now, what were we talking about? Ah,
so even though you've got the blood coming out of the female
genitalia or the semen coming out of the male, nevertheless, you can't
say it's a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, because בעל קרי ba'al keri
is only for men, and נדה niddah is only—we'll talk about it—and
נדה's niddah only for women. So therefore, if he's not a man
or not a woman, or not clear how to label, then even
though it's the right liquids and fluids and the right genitalia, unless
the person is defined as a man or a woman, he's not
a בעל קרי ba'al keri and not a נדה. niddah. או זב
או זבה? o zav o zavah? What? Not that either, no. Okay,
so if someone has no questions, let's go on. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So now, that's if one or the other
came out. Now what if both came out? ראו לובן ואודם כאחד,
ra'u loven ve'odem ke'echad, let's say both came out. So both came
out. So by the אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, if both came out, you could
still say maybe this person is a third gender and maybe nothing.
Okay, at least you could understand how you'd get that. But by
the טומטום, tumtum, you would assume well, he's either one or the
other; both came out, so he's got to be either a בעל
קרי ba'al keri or a נדה. niddah. Either way, אין חייבין על
ביאת מקדש; ein chayavin al biyas mikdash; nevertheless, if that person were
to walk into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, he would not get
כרת, kares, would not have to bring a קרבן. korban. אבל שורפין
עליהם את התרומה; aval sorfin aleihem es haterumah; definitely you would burn
the תרומה, terumah, because in that case, he's definitely טמא. tamei, You
just don't know as a—as a בעל קרי ba'al keri or as
a נדה. niddah. Now, by the way, saying that you would burn
תרומה terumah and definitely טמא tamei, means that presumably by the אנדרוגינוס
androgynos as well, we're not sort of assuming that it's a third
category. We're assuming, because if it was a third category, then by
the אנדרוגינוס androgynos you wouldn't say definitely טמא, tamei? right? Is that
right? So presumably we're assuming that אנדרוגינוס androgynos is either/or, we don't
know which; טומטום tumtum is definitely either/or. And nevertheless, even when both
things happen, we cannot—they're definitely טמא, tamei because this guy's either a
בעל קרי ba'al keri or נדה, niddah, definitely טמא, tamei, right? We
just don't know how to categorize. Nevertheless, they're not חייב chayav for
going into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Why not? Alright, so let's
take a look. אנדרוגינוס Androgynos can breed himself? I don't know. I
don't mean literally, physically, but if the semen—I have no idea. Biologically,
I assume not. I mean, I don't know enough to comment. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: דנאמר—why denemar not, if it's
definitely טמא? tamei, So again, this implicitly says that אנדרוגינוס androgynos is
not a third category. So we're dealing here with somebody that's either
male or female, we just don't know either how to categorize or
we don't know the facts, and definitely טמא tamei, therefore, but not
חייב. chayav. Why not? שנאמר מזכר ועד נקבה תשלחו, shenemar mizachar ve'ad
nekevah teshalechu, you shall send out from male to female. זכר ודאי
ונקבה ודאית. zachar vadai unekevah vedais. Only the person that—somebody is only
חייב chayav although they're definitely טמא, tamei if you're not definitely having
an identity as male or female, you are not חייב. chayav. That
idea of sending out of the camp is the flip of the
prohibition of going in when you're טמא, tamei and you're not חייב
chayav for entering in when you're... How, how and everybody in between,
that’s a good point, yeah. So this brings up the modern question
of a transsexual, it's a halakhic question. Yeah, but that’s, yes. I
mean, obviously within this and within the גמרא Gemara discussing identifying gender,
they have to discuss what’s the status of a transsexual nowadays, post-op,
pre-op, and all those things; separate conversation, but absolutely those are very
relevant questions. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, זכר
ודאי ונקבה ודאי zachar vadai u’nekeivah vadai ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, v’lo tumtum
v’androgynos, and now a טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, which is quite
interesting because you would say, and תוספות sort of says, what do
you mean? I mean, like, you know, a טומטום tumtum is a
ודאי זכר או נקבה, vadai zachar o nekeivah, I mean we just
don't know, you know, or even an אנדרוגינוס androgynos תוספות says, just
because we don't know how to פסקן paskin doesn't mean that God
doesn't know what halakhic category it falls into, though there you could
say not necessarily לא בשמים היא; lo bashamayim hee; if we haven't
פסקנד, paskened, then God also doesn't, you know, hasn't defined yet, but
certainly טומטום tumtum God knows, we just don't know. So תוספות says,
yeah, it's not like a normal ספק, safeik, here's a ספק safeik
generated by a different physical reality, so in a way we're saying
this is not a classic male, classic female, it's not just like
we don't know the facts. Normally you would never say just because
we happen not to know the facts the הלכה halakha changes, you
know; here it's that there's something physical about even the טומטום tumtum
case which makes the gender indeterminate. So when something about the body
leads to an indeterminate identification of gender, that classifies them out of
this classic זכר ונקבה zachar v’nekeivah category and therefore they're not חייב.
chayav. Now, one interesting way about thinking about this is that since
בעל קרי ba’al keri and נידה niddah are both, if you remember
from the גמרא Gemara before, have an idea of רואה ro’eh not
נוגע, nogeia, it's not because they touched their blood and their semen,
it's because about their personal status, and their personal status has very
much to do with their gender. It's, we're talking about the types
of liquids that are very much about their maleness and femaleness, so
you could understand that the idea here is is that while let’s
say the semen or the blood might be טמא, tamei they and
they are טמא tamei, if they touch שרץ sheretz and all of
that, it's not that full level of טומאה tumah because it's not
about, you know, it's not create like that full sense of personal
status which is all connected to their gender when their gender is
itself indeterminate. So there's something, I think, very logical about this, it's
not just גזירת הכתוב, gezeirat hakatuv, because we're talking specifically about a
טומאה tumah that is very gender related. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: so they're not allowed to go in the
מקדש? Mikdash? Right, right, right, they're just not חייב. chayav. Right, right,
right. לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesayei lei, let me try to prove
this, טומטום ואנדרוגינוס שראו לובן או אודם, tumtum v’androgynos sherau loven o
odem, that the טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgynos saw either white or
red, אין חייבין על ביאת מקדש ואין שורפין עליהם את התרומה, ein
chayavin al biat Mikdash v’ein sorfin aleihem et haterumah, they're not חייבין
chayavin for going to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as ספק, safeik,
and not only that, you wouldn't burn תרומה, terumah, it's not definite
טמא tamei, because they might be the other gender. ראו לובן ואודם
כאחד, rau loven v’odem k’echad, if you saw both, אין חייבין על
ביאת מקדש, ein chayavin al biat Mikdash, you're not חייבין chayavin for
going to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, אבל שורפין עליהם את התרומה,
aval sorfin aleihem et haterumah, they're definitely טמא tamei, and you burn
the תרומה, terumah, so you see that's exactly what you said, and
here we have a ברייתא braita that repeats it. מאי טעמא, mai
ta’ama, what's the reason of this ברייתא? braita? לאו משום שנאמר מזכר
ועד נקבה תשלחו, lav mishum shene’emar mizachar v’ad nekeivah tishaleichu, isn't it
because of the פסוק pasuk you quoted, זכר ודאי ונקבה ודאי, zachar
vadai u’nekeivah vadai, only definite male, definite female are, you know, transgress
when they go into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash for this gender
טומאה, tumah ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, v’lo tumtum v’androgynos, and not טומטום tumtum
and אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. So it seems like exactly what you said for
the same reason. אמר עולא לא, amar Ulla lo, no, maybe this
is what you said, but maybe for a very different reason. המני
רבי אליעזר היא, hamanee Rabbi Eliezer hee, maybe this is Rabbi Eliezer,
דתנן, detnan, as the משנה says, רבי אליעזר אומר השרץ ונעלם ממנו,
Rabbi Eliezer omer hasheretz v’ne’elam mimenu, so the פסוק pasuk says if
somebody touches a שרץ sheretz and it's hidden from him and they
go into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, then they're חייב chayav a
קרבן. korban. So what is hidden? There has to be a העלמה,
halamah, there has to be something you, it's not במזיד, b’meizid, it's
בשוגג. b’shogeg. So Rabbi Eliezer, so there are a couple things that
could be hidden: you forgot that you were טמא, tamei. or you
forgot it was a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, or in theory you
also could have known all of that and forgot it was אסור,
assur, but let's bracket that for a moment. So which of the
facts did you not, were you, did you forget when you did
this transgression בשוגג b’shogeg and are going to have to bring a
קרבן? korban? So Rabbi Eliezer says the פסוק pasuk says first it
speaks about שרץ sheretz and then it says hidden, על העלם שרץ
הוא חייב ואינו חייב על העלם מקדש, al he’elem sheretz hu chayav
v’eino chayav al he’elem Mikdash, you only bring a קרבן korban if
you forgot that you had touched the שרץ, sheretz, not if you
forgot that you were about to enter the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
רבי עקיבא אומר ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא, Rabbi Akiva omer v’ne’elam mimenu
v’hu tamei, it's hidden from you and you are טמא, tamei, meaning
it's hidden from you that you are טמא, tamei על העלם טומאה
הוא חייב ואינו חייב על העלם מקדש, al he’elem tumah hu chayav
v’eino chayav al he’elem Mikdash, you're only חייב chayav a קרבן; korban;
obviously you transgressed, but you're only חייב chayav a קרבן korban under
very particular circumstances when it is hidden from you that you were
טמא. tamei, So Rabbi Eliezer says when it's hidden from you that
you touched the שרץ sheretz and Rabbi Akiva says when it's hidden
from you that you were טמא, tamei... both say if you know
you're טמא Tamei, but it's hidden from you the מקדש, Mikdash, that's
not a basis for bringing a קרבן. korban. You can understand the
logic, by the way: if you know you're טמא, Tamei first of
all it's absurd anyway how somebody can not realize they're about to
enter into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and if you know you're
טמא... Tamei Then you have to in general be more aware, have
your guard up about not doing something wrong. So that case maybe
is not deserving of a קרבן, Korban, but if it's hidden from
you that you're טמא, Tamei that's different. If you forgot about that.
Now, one says about the שרץ Sheretz and the other says טומאה,
tumah. but they're the same. They're both saying you forgot you were
טמא Tamei. or it was hidden from you. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ואמינא V'amina and we said מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu?
What's, how are they different? They both say you have to forget
you're טמא Tamei. or be hidden from you. So אמר חזקיה, Amar
Chizkiyah, שרץ ונבלה איכא בינייהו. sheretz u'neveilah ika beinaihu. The difference is
that there was a שרץ sheretz and a נבלה neveilah and you
touched one of them and you know you're טמא Tamei but you
don't know how you got to be טמא. Tamei רבי אליעזר סבר
בעינן עד דידע אי בשרץ איטמי אי בנבלה איטמי. Rabbi Eliezer savar
beinan ad d'yada i b'sheretz itmei i b'neveilah itmei. Rabbi Eliezer says
you have to know specifically how you became טמא. Tamei. If you
just knew you were generically טמא tamei and you didn't know how
and you forgot that, that would not be enough to be, that
would not satisfy the criteria of bringing a קרבן. Korban. You have
to know the specific, so whatever, you do תשובה, teshuvah, but you
don't bring the קרבן. Korban. Okay, whereas he says השרץ ונעלם. ha'sheretz
v'ne'elam. There has to be a specific knowledge of your טומאה tumah
and that be hidden. ורבי עקיבא סבר לא בעינן. V'Rabbi Akiva savar
lo beinan. You don't need it. As long as you know you're
טמא tamei and that's hidden from you. So let's just connect the
dots. לאו אמר רבי אליעזר התם. Lav amar Rabbi Eliezer hatam. The
same way Rabbi Eliezer says there בעינן דידע אי בשרץ איטמי אי
בנבלה איטמי. beinan d'yada i b'sheretz itmei i b'neveilah itmei. You have
to know the nature of your טומאה tumah. and then remember it
afterwards because only after you remember do you bring the קרבן. Korban.
הכא נמי בעינן דידע אי בלבן איטמי אי באודם איטמי. Hacha nami
beinan d'yada i b'lavan itmei i b'odem itmei. Here too you have
to know the specific nature of your טומאה. tumah So you know
what? Maybe it's not זכר ונקבה. zachar u'nekeivah. Maybe actually if you
went in במזיד b'meizid you would get מלקות. malkos. That's not the
issue. The issue is to be חייב קרבן. chayav korban. To be
חייב קרבן chayav korban according to רבי אליעזר, there's a specific criteria,
you have to know exactly how you became טמא. tamei And here
you don't know, you're either טמא Tamei, as a נדה niddah or
you're טמא Tamei. as a בעל קרי. baal keri. You don't know
which one. So in that type of a case you cannot be
חייב קרבן chayav korban according to רבי אליעזר. הכא נמי, Hacha nami,
here too, הכא נמי בעינן דידע. hacha nami beinan d'yada. You have
both, but you're only טמא tamei based on one of them because
you're only either male or female. הכא נמי בעינן דידע אי בלבן
איטמי אי באודם איטמי. Hacha nami beinan d'yada i b'lavan itmei i
b'odem itmei. אבל רבי עקיבא דאמר משום טומאה מחייב. Aval Rabbi Akiva
d'amar mishum tumah mechayev. According to Rabbi Akiva that it's enough to
just know you're טמא, tamei. הכא נמי משום טומאה מחייב. hacha nami
mishum tumah mechayev. Here too it's enough. So there is an opinion,
yes, you have a lovely ברייתא braita that says that even if
you had both the blood and the semen you're not חייב chayav
from מקדש, Mikdash, but maybe that's not because you're excluded from the
פסוק. pasuk. Maybe if you did it במזיד b'meizid you'd get מלקות,
malkos, but maybe it's just because to be חייב קרבן chayav korban
you need the specific knowledge of how you became טמא. tamei? Charlie.
So there's two ways you could not know whether you're טמא tamei.
from a נבלה neveilah or from a שרץ. sheretz. One is there
was a שרץ sheretz in front of you and a נבלה neveilah
in front of you and you tripped over one and you didn't
see which one you tripped over. Another issue is there's one animal
there, it's a small animal and you touch it and you know
it was dead but you aren't sure whether that animal is one
of the, one of the animals that's called שרץ. sheretz. Okay, it's
a good point. So there's, I don't think there's a difference regarding
this, that's my point. Yeah, you mean it might apply to the
שרץ ונבלה sheretz u'neveilah because that is true, it's most analogous to
that case, you have both things and then you don't know which
one to attribute it to as opposed to, I would assume the
other case is even more generic and even less השרץ ונעלם. ha'sheretz
v'ne'elam. In one case you knew there was a שרץ. sheretz. Here
you don't even know. I don't know, I'd have to see, it
would depend anyway how we פסקן, pasken, we'd only be able to
find out if we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר anyway or if
there was more discussion about it. But yeah, those could, you could
in theory sort of like the whole case about the אשם תלוי
asham talui about an abstract doubt as opposed to a concrete doubt,
you could in theory make a distinction. Yes. What would be an
example of the drug and the different sexual things? Is that just
educational or is that practical? Yeah, I think it's more, I think,
I don't know, I don't know how many אנדרוגינוס androgynus you had
in that time, but I think it always leads to, the גמרא
Gemara is interested in the more outline cases. The straightforward ones are
easy, what's there to discuss? So the same way we discuss fetuses
that look like, you know, that had different animal-like appearances, we talk
about these unusual cases of identifying gender. It could have happened, you
know, once every thousand or ten thousand times, but the, but the
amount that they're discussing it does not reflect the proportion of how
much it actually occurred in the real world. Can an אנדרוגינוס androgynus
become pregnant or impregnate somebody else? Not clear. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. I have to look, there might be some
discussion, I don't remember. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where were we? Ah, so it might be רבי אליעזר. ורב, V'Rav,
and Rav would say, מאי שנא ביאת מקדש? mai shna bias Mikdash?
Where's Rav? Rav was the he was the one that said, he
was the one that said זכר ונקבה zachar u'nekeivah that it's a
גזירת הכתוב g'zeiras ha'kasuv if you're not definitely male, definitely female. So
the גמרא Gemara says and it's not based on this פסוק pasuk
about השרץ ונעלם, ha'sheretz v'ne'elam, it's not just about the קרבן. korban.
So ורב, V'Rav, according to Rav that emphasizes definite male. and female.
מאי שנא ביאת מקדש דלא, mai shna bias mikdash delo, why do
you exclude them from going into בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, דכתיב מזכר
ועד נקבה תשלחו, d'ketiv mizachar v'ad nekeivah tishaleichu, from male to female,
זכר ועד נקבה ודאי, zachar v'ad nekeivah vaday, definite male, definite female,
ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, v'lo tumtum v'androginos, not טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. androginos.
אי הכי, ei hachi, תרומה נמי לא נשרף? terumah nami lo nisraf?
So then you shouldn't even consider them definitely טמא. tamei. Why do
we consider them definitely טמא? tamei. Don't even burn תרומה, terumah, don't
consider them definitely טמא. tamei Why not? דכתיב, d'ketiv, it says, והזב
והזבה לזכר ולנקבה. ve'hazav ve'hazavah lazachar velanekeivah. The פסוק pasuk which is
talking about all the טומאות, tumos, not about going into the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but just the fact of טומאה, tumah at the
end of that at the end it says and the one who
has the flow whether male or female. So maybe and they're talking
about the fact that you're טמא. tamei, So why not say זכר
ודאי ונקבה ודאית, zachar vaday u'nekeivah vadayis, only definite male and definite
female has that status of זב zav or נדה niddah or יולדת,
yoledes, ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, v'lo tumtum v'androginos, and not a טומטום tumtum
and אנדרוגינוס. androginos. Which makes a certain amount of sense as I
was saying, if you emphasize that this is about personal status and
as a personal status that's very much related to gender, semen and
hymenal bleeding and so on, maybe you don't even have that טומאה
tumah if you're not a definite male or female. Says גמרא Gemara
says, no, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יצחק. hahu miba'ei lei lich'derabbi yitzchak.
That פסוק pasuk of לזכר ולנקבה lazachar velanekeivah by טומאה tumah is
not used to exclude טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס, androginos, they are טמא.
tamei, It's used to teach me what רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says.
דאמר רבי יצחק, d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, says רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, לזכר,
lazachar, לרבות את המצורע למעיינותיו. lerabbos es hametzora lema'ayanosav. The male includes
another type of a male, includes the מצורע metzora for his wellsprings.
לנקבה lenekeivah and a female is another female that's not which is
not just the זב zav and the נדה, niddah, לרבות את המצורעת
למעיינותיה, lerabbos es hametzora'as lema'ayanoseha, the female מצורע metzora for her wellsprings.
What does this mean? The תורה Torah says by a זב, zav,
וכי ירוק הזב בטהור, v'chi yarok hazav batahor, it says that the
spit of a זב zav is טמא tamei and we've discussed this
before, it's an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. It's not just because he
touched the spit, it's actually seen as a primary source of טומאה
tumah and similar certain other types of fluids that come from a
זב, zav, זבה, zavah, and a נדה niddah are אב הטומאה. av
hatumah. Those fluids, not all, but some of them are considered to
be מעיינות, ma'ayanos, the wellsprings of a זב zav and a זבה.
zavah. Now, the תורה Torah never says this by a מצורע. metzora.
A זב zav and a זבה zavah you understand why there might
be wellsprings because their טומאה tumah, came from certain flowing liquids. So
maybe there's a similar concept, all of these types of liquids have
a special טומאה. tumah But a מצורע metzora that it's nothing about
that, it's about spots on the skin, maybe it doesn't have that
same הלכה. halacha. So says רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, because the תורה
Torah wraps up that whole פרשה parsha about זב zav and זבה
zavah and the whole thing and says לזכר ולנקבה, lazachar velanekeivah, it
means even other males and females that have similar personal טומאה tumah
statuses have same הלכות. halachos. Even מצורע, metzora, if a מצורע metzora
spits on you, the spit of a מצורע metzora is also an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. That's what he learns from it, not to
exclude טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androginos from the טומאה. tumah, Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says, oh, okay, so if you say I can't use
that because it's being used somewhere else, so האי נמי מיבעי ליה.
hai nami miba'ei lei. So by the case about having to get
out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, having that לזכר ולנקבה, lazachar
velanekeivah, I learn something else from that פסוק pasuk לזכר ולנקבה. lazachar
velanekeivah. What do I learn from it? במי שיש לו טהרה במקוה,
bemi sheyesh lo tahara bemikveh, that you're only prohibited and you only
have to get out something that is similar to male and female.
What's true about male and female? That when they become טמא, tamei.
they can become טהור tahor by going into a מקוה. mikveh. But
if something cannot become טהור tahor by going into a מקוה, mikveh,
like a כלי חרס, kli cheres, you can't become טהור. tahor. So
if a כלי חרס kli cheres is טמא, tamei you actually do
not have to get it out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Pretty wild. Okay. So במי שיש לו טהרה במקוה, bemi sheyesh lo
tahara bemikveh, פרט לכלי חרס, prat likli cheres, דברי רבי יוסי. divrei
Rabbi Yossi. That's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi said. Now, by the
way, let me just clarify one point. רש"י and תוספות say this
but I'll try to sort of summarize it. The point is like
this, normally you don't have to go out, nobody who got contact
טומאה tumah from outside have to go out of, the only place
that they're not allowed is the מקדש. Mikdash. They're even allowed in
מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, which would be like הר הבית. Har HaBayis.
The biggest example is that even a corpse, it says ויקח משה
את עצמות יוסף עמו, vayikach Moshe es atzmos Yosef imo, that means
that he actually brought the corpse with him in מחנה לויה, machaneh
leviyah, and he became טמא tamei through touching it and the corpse
itself was טמא. tamei So things that are not number one טומאה
יוצא מגופו, tumah yotzei migufo, about personal status, and certainly things that
טומאה tumah, comes from the outside, you're allowed up to הר הבית.
Har HaBayis. The only thing you can't go into is the מקדש.
Mikdash. So if you have a normal כלי kli that became טמא
tamei. through touching something, a metal vessel touched a מת or whatever
it touched, a זב, zav, זבה zavah or whatever, something that a
vessel because the vessel only becomes טמא tamei. from the outside, right?
So that thing would anyway obviously be allowed in מחנה לויה. machaneh
leviyah. So if we're making an exception about a pottery vessel, we're
not making the exception in מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, any טמא tamei
vessel can be in מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, because it's all about
טומאה tumah from the outside. So what we're actually doing is we're
making an exception even in מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, even in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that is the only place that you have
to get rid of all טומאה tumah even when it came from
the outside, even things that... Why is it if the טומאה is
on the inside but not on the outside? No, because it's because
it's because it's because it's because it's because it's because it's like
we learned from the פסוק pasuk of מזכר עד נקבה mizachar ad
nekeivah that only things you have to get rid of in מחנה
שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, even when it's the weakest טומאה, and even when
it's from the outside, that's only from things that you can dunk
in the מקוה. mikvah. But a כלי חרס kli cheres that is
not a source of טומאה and that cannot be טהרה במקוה, tahara
bi-mikvah, does not have to be get rid of even from מחנה
שכינה. Machaneh Shechinah. But you don't want טמאי כלים tamei keilim in
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Yeah, they're practical reasons, but you're not
עובר over on a לאו. lav. Okay? Practically you don't want it
around. Okay. There's even some discussion, by the way, which I'm not
going to get into, by the מנחת חינוך Minchas Chinuch about what
about a שרץ sheretz itself? That's not a... that doesn't have טהרה
במקוה, tahara bi-mikvah, right? So, maybe you can have... it made it
so... it made it so... but that you can't. Anyway, let's move
on. For now the גמרא Gemara, just mentioned כלי חרס. kli cheres.
So anyway, that's what you need the פסוק pasuk for. So the
גמרא Gemara says, No, אם כן נכתוב רחמנא אדם. im kein nichtov
rachmana adam. If it just wanted to exclude to say it has
to be like people that has טהרה במקוה, tahara bi-mikvah, it would
have said person. Why male female is to exclude these unusual genders.
וכי תימא אי כתב רחמנא אדם, ve-chi teima i katav rachmana adam,
if it just said person, הוה אמינא כלי מתכות לא, hava amina
kley matches lo, it would have to be literally a person, and
therefore there would not be an obligation to get rid of even
metal vessels that became טמא. tamei, So, מכל טמא לנפש נפקא. mikol
tamei lenefesh nafka. No, because the verse says anything that became טמא.
tamei, So, the combination of אדם, adam which is very limiting, and
anything that became טמא tamei would have translated into anything similar to
אדם Adam, that has טהרה במקוה. tahara bi-mikvah. And I would have
known to say you gotta get rid of metal vessels, but pottery
vessels are not a problem. So there would have been another way
to learn that out. זכר ונקבה למה לי? Zachar unekeivah lama li?
Why did the Torah have to go so far to say male
female? לכדי רב, le-chidei Rav, to tell me what רב Rav said,
that only definite male, definite female are חייב. chayav. They are טמא,
but they are not חייב chayav unless you know, a mixed gender,
whatever, undetermined gender is טמא, but not חייב chayav unless it's definite
male, definite female. So like the pottery vessel? What? Are they like
the pottery vessel? No well, in terms of the הלכה halakha that
you're not חייב. chayav. ואימא כולה לכדי רב הוא דאתאי, ve-eima kulei
le-chidei Rav hu de-asyei, maybe it's only telling you that and not
telling you this הלכה halakha pottery vessels, only telling you this הלכה
halakha of definite gender? No, אם כן נכתוב זכר ונקבה, im kein
nichtov zachar unekeivah, male and female. מאי מזכר עד נקבה? Mai mizachar
ad nekeivah? There you go, until female. עד כל דבר שיש לו
טהרה במקוה Ad kol davar she-yeish lo tahara bi-mikvah means anything like
male and female, meaning that has טהרה במקוה, tahara bi-mikvah, but something
like a כלי חרס, kli cheres, no. And again, a person that's
not a definite זכר zachar and not נקבה, nekeivah, also not. אי
הכי, I hachi, כי תני ki itnei now one last question the
גמרא Gemara says: כי תני ki itnei if you're excluding male and
female, I've been saying male and female when it's about a טומאה
about their personal status and connected to their gender. But the גמרא
says let's do this reductio ad absurdum. Only a definite male definite
female have to be sent out of the מקום מקדש. Makom Mikdash.
So let's say you have a טומטום tumtum and androgynous that touches
a מת. Does he not have to be sent out of the
בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Because is maybe it completely excludes people that
aren't definite male definite female? אי הכי I hachi says the גמרא,
כי תני ki itnei בשאר טומאות, bishar tumas, even if he becomes
טמא otherwise by touching a מת, לא לשלחו, lo leshalchu, he shouldn't
have to be sent out, because he's not זכר zachar or נקבה,
nekeivah, you know, in an unambiguous way. אמר קרא: Amar kra: מזכר,
mi-zachar, from the male, meaning מטומאה הפורשת מן הזכר, mi-tumah ha-poreshos min
hazachar, from a male type of טומאה, it comes from the maleness
almost if you will. And that's the point. We're not excluding טומטום
tumtum and androgynous from the whole הלכה. halakha. We're saying the טומאה
that results from their gender, that type of a טומאה, the טומאה
about their maleness, about femaleness, then you're only חייב chayav if you're
definite male definite female, not if you're in the ambiguous state, which
makes a lot of sense. As I said, you could have gone
so far to say maybe you don't even have the טומאה at
all, but the גמרא stops, you know, does not go that far.
And I guess we will stop with this. Should we do five
more? Oh yeah, you know what, let's do that. Let's go again.
Yeah, you're right. Let's do five let's do let's do the five
more lines. Okay, thank you. וכל היכא דכתיב מזכר נקבה Ve-chol haycha
de-chasiv mi-zachar nekeivah to exclude טומטום tumtum and ואנדרוגינוס androgynos is what
it's for? Does male female always exclude טומטום tumtum and ואנדרוגינוס? androgynos?
והא גבי ערכין דכתיב הזכר, Ve-ha gabbei archin de-chasiv hazachar, it says
הזכר, hazachar, the male. Remember we learned ערכין? Arachin? דתניא, De-tanya, הזכר,
hazachar, the male, ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, velo tumtum ve-androgynos, not these people.
יכול לא יהא בערך איש ולא יהא בערך אשה? Yachol lo yehei
beerach ish velo yehei beerach isha? Fine, they don't have the higher
ערך erech of the man, maybe they have the lower ערך erech
of the woman? Because they you know, you can't obligate me to
pay for the man, maybe this person wasn't a man when I
said his ערך, erech, he doesn't necessarily fit in the man category,
but at least pay the lower ערך erech of the woman? תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar הזכר ואם נקבה, hazachar ve-im nekeivah, the male and
linked to female. זכר ודאי ונקבה ודאי, Zachar vaday unekeivah vaday, only
definite male definite female do you pay ערך erech when but ולא
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, velo tumtum ve-androgynos, not טומטום tumtum and ואנדרוגינוס androgynos that
you cannot definitely put in one category or the other. So why
is that a question? טעמא דכתיב הזכר... Taama de-chasiv hazachar... The emphasis
there seems to be the ה, Heh, the, the definite male, the
ואם נקבה. ve'im nikeiva. היי Hai זכר ונקבה, Zachar venikeiva, if it
just said a male without the ה, Heh, the לא ממעט, lo
mima'et, so I would not have excluded. So it's saying yes, yes,
we use זכר ונקבה Zachar venikeiva to exclude טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, Tumtum ve'androgynos,
but there it's because of the ה, Heh, the, which means the
definite male. Without the ה Heh here, how are you entitled to
exclude? So the גמרא says no. ההוא מיבעי ליה לחלק בין ערך
איש לערך אשה. Hahu mibayei lei lachaleik bein erech ish le'erech isha.
There the תורה Torah anyway had to say male and female. It
had to tell you here the costs for the male, here the
costs for the female. It had to use the word male, female;
had no choice. So the only way we could exclude, say definite
male, was the extra letter of ה, Heh, הזכר. Hazachar. Just say
male, female was a necessary part of how to express what was
going on. In our case, it didn't have to say male and
female. It could've just said אדם, everybody. So by saying male, female,
even without the ה, Heh, it means only definite genders and excludes
the case of טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Tumtum ve'androgynos.